start with two angles alpha and beta
both in the interval zero to pi over two
draw a triangle with horizontal base and
an altitude that cuts the triangle into
pieces with angle alpha and angle beta
let's suppose that the legs on this
triangle are called a and b
the area of this triangle can be
determined using the side angle side
formula for the area of the triangle and
is thus one half a times b times the
sine of alpha plus beta
suppose the altitude from the angle
alpha plus beta has length y
this altitude cuts the triangle into two
sub-triangles that are both right
triangles and both with a side length of
y
according to the left triangle y is
adjacent to alpha so y is equal to a
times the cosine of alpha and in the
right triangle y is adjacent to beta so
y is equal to b times the cosine of beta
but the value y is part of both
triangles so we can use opposite values
on opposite triangles like this
now the original triangle must have area
given by the sum of the areas of the two
sub triangles
but these two areas can be computed
using the side angle side formula for a
triangle again so we have that one
triangle is one half times a times b
times the cosine of beta times sine of
alpha and the other one is one half b
times a cosine alpha times the sine of
beta
we can cancel the one half a times b
from both sides of this equation and
that results in the formula sine of
alpha plus beta equals the sine of alpha
times the cosine of beta plus the cosine
of alpha times the sine of beta
this is the sine of a sum formula